Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ה, mem-hey, we
kick off on the bottom of מ"ד עמוד ב'. mem-dalet amud-bet. We
are in the middle of a whole discussion about being a witness
testifying on land or on anything, but that through your testimony you
might stand to have some type of a gain and that that
makes you invalid to testify and trying to figure out what are
those circumstances. So we pick up four lines from
the bottom, גופא. Gufa. אמר רבינא בר שילא בשם שמואל: Amar Ravina
bar Shila b'shem Shmuel: המוכר שדה לחבירו שלא באחריות. Ha-mocher sadeh l'chaveiro
shelo b'achrayut. Somebody, Reuven, sells to Shimon a field and he does
not give him insurance. He does not tell Shimon that he will
reimburse him if the field is taken. Because if he gives him
insurance, it's patently obvious that he can't testify on behalf of Shimon.
That's protecting him from having to pay out the insurance. But you
might think if he didn't give Shimon insurance and if the field
is taken from Shimon he will not have to pay out, so
you might think that he would be able to testify that the
field is legitimately Shimon's. Nevertheless he says, אין מעיד לו עליו. Ein
me-id lo alav. He cannot testify to keep the field in Shimon's
possession. Why? מפני שעומדת בפני בעל חובו. Mipnei she-omedet bifnei ba'al chovo.
This is what we've discussed now the third time this is being
quoted.
Because Reuven still benefits from the fact that it's in Shimon's possession
rather than it had always belonged to Yehuda. So when Reuven's creditors
come to Reuven and Reuven doesn't have the money to pay, they'll
be able to collect from Shimon because it went through Reuven to
Shimon. And if it proves that it's not Shimon's because it was
never not just never Shimon's, it was never Reuven's, it was always
somebody else's, then the creditor won't be paid. So he has that
indirect benefit that it could be collected
by creditors. Again, it seems like we do not ask a case-by-case
scenario of like what if in this particular circumstance there are no
creditors. Although or you know if Reuven is very wealthy and we're
not concerned about that.
Although again I'll remind you yesterday we had a little קימטא kimta
about some type of cases like oh if you bought something and
sold it right away or if you never had land or whatever
in that case like you remember some of those answers we had
yesterday in that case you would be allowed to testify. So it
actually sounds a little bit from yesterday that this isn't categorical. That
if we could actually prove that somebody is free of interest it
might be okay. All right but as a rule we're not going
to let somebody testify because we assume that there will be some
gain. Now היכי דמי? Heichi Dami? What's the case? asks the גמרא.
Gemara. דף מ"ה עמוד א'. Daf mem-hey amud-aleph. אי דאית ליה ארעא
אחריתי עליה דידיה הדר. Ee d'is lei ara achriti alei didey hadar.
So here the גמרא Gemara exactly does exactly that. It says let's
look and decide not just is there or isn't there creditors because
that's like the hardest thing to decide. Who knows if there's some
creditor somewhere that we don't know about and how do you prove
a negative? But let's see by some of the circumstances if there
is really some gain you know
and the easiest thing to test for is like I said before
is Reuven wealthy? Is there other stuff the creditor could collect from?
And if there's plenty of other stuff that the creditor could collect
from then Reuven does not really gain anything. So if he has
more land עליה דידיה הדר alei didey hadar the creditor will come
straight to Reuven. So it doesn't matter that Shimon has land, Reuven
has land. So אי דלית ליה ארעא אחריתי Ee d'leis lei ara
achriti and if he has no other land... so now I just
want to pause for a moment on that. Why do you think
it says if Reuven has land then he doesn't benefit? Why didn't
it say if Reuven has ten million dollars in the bank? Yes
it's easier to get access to something that is land. It's way
easier to get access, not only is it easier to get access,
meaning it can't get lost, it can't disappear. You can gamble away
your ten million dollars, you can invest it and lose the stock
or whatever. What's the worst that could happen to land? You could
sell it. Well if you sold it, then he gets to collect
from the land. So if there's other land, forget other money presumably
doesn't matter. There's still going to be a benefit because fortunes go
up and fortunes go down. But if there's other land for the
creditor to collect from then even if you didn't have this land
available for the creditor he will always have other land. Now you
might say maybe the other land isn't as good, maybe whatever, but
point is who cares, we're talking about whether you benefit so it
might be worse off for the creditor to get from this land
than the other land, but at least you're going to get your
debt paid off. Okay so if Reuven has other land then we
know that the creditor will regardless get his debt paid off and
therefore he would be able to testify. Now in theory I could
actually make still a distinction which is I have a thousand dollar
debt on me, I sell this land to Eli
and I want to testify... but I have three other plots of
land, I want to testify that it's Eli's so well I'm not
going to gain anything because the creditor could always collect from those
other plots of land but you know what I'm going to gain
from? Now I want to borrow ten thousand dollars from you. If
I only had... if I now have three unencumbered plots of land
you're going to lend me the money. But if I actually have
only two unencumbered plots of land because that land from Eli was
taken away and now one of these lands another person has first
dibs on, so I have less unencumbered property right and then maybe
you'll be more hesitant to lend me money. People sort of see
that? Right? So the amount of total assets, maybe this, the particular
בעלי חוב Ba'alei Chov creditors you have will get paid up right
away, okay, but it doesn't mean that you're not going to gain
for the fact you have more assets. Or I can give you
another case. Let's say I have more, let's say I have number
of creditors equal to my full debt. I have two creditors, I
owe each of them two thousand dollars, each of them a thousand
dollars.
Each plot of land is worth a thousand. One plot of land
is sold to Eli and one plot of land I still have.
So if we say oh, I'm allowed to testify because creditor number
one can still collect from this plot of land, but no, creditor
number two is then going to be out, right? So if I
am losing, I'm shrinking the available assets I have for creditors to
collect from, there actually is still some law. Why can't creditor number
two take it from the look, from the look? No, that's why
he can't if I testified it belonged to Eli. But if it
turns out it never belonged to him and I'm allowed to testify
it belongs to him, oh maybe, but I thought I did, I
might be making this too complicated. Here's ראובן. Reuven. He sells to
שמעון Shimon one plot of land. That's not what he looked like
yesterday. I know. So he sells to שמעון Shimon one plot of
land. That's worth a thousand dollars. Okay. And he has a creditor,
we'll call him לוי, Levi, okay. He lent him a thousand dollars.
Okay. And he I have another plot of land, also worth a
thousand. So we're going to say I can testify that that land
is שמעון Shimon's because I don't gain that that, the reason I
shouldn't be able to testify is I gain that לוי Levi then
collects from it. But I'm not going to gain in this case
because לוי Levi can only just collect from this plot of land.
Okay, but what about a scenario where there's two creditors?
Okay?
Right? So it might be that this creditor has this plot, this
creditor can collect from this, but this guy will be out. By
keeping this land in the hand of שמעון, Shimon, I'm allowing both
of them to, but the key is is that you're, you sold
it to שמעון Shimon בלי אחריות. Beli Achrayus. If you sold it
to שמעון Shimon with אחריות, Achrayus, בלי אחריות Beli Achrayus means I
don't have to reimburse שמעון Shimon if it gets taken away. I
see, but if you sold it to שמעון Shimon with אחריות, Achrayus,
then all of your land ends up being encumbered anyway. Right, so
I certainly can't testify if it's sold to him with אחריות. Achrayus.
I'm just saying that even without אחריות, Achrayus, okay, it's not so
clear just because I have other land that means that this doesn't
benefit me. This does benefit me. We don't know how much my
outstanding debts are. And when you don't know how much my outstanding
debts are, having one more piece of land to collect from even
if we know I have plenty can still help me. But okay,
the גמרא Gemara's willing to say that. Let's read it again. אי
דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי, Ei De'is Lei Ara Acharisi, maybe we're not
going to just worry that far because we don't even know if
there are creditors. So since it's all hypothetical, we're not going to
go that far. If we think we actually knew, it might change?
No, but it means the whole, anyway, maybe, maybe we'd be more
concerned because we already know there are x number of creditors, I
don't know. אי דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי Ei De'is Lei Ara Acharisi
עליה דידי הדר. Alei Didi Hadar. So if there's, if he has
other, there's plenty of land, we're not going to be concerned that
this one plot he loses, he stands to gain. There's plenty of
other land available for the creditors. Now, אי ד, Ei De, so
then he should be able to testify. אי דלית ליה ארעא אחריתי,
Ei Deleis Lei Ara Acharisi, if he doesn't have any other land,
מאי נפקא ליה מיניה. Mai Nafka Lei Minei. So let's say the
case of, he doesn't have any land and we're afraid that he's
going to, if he's going to benefit because he'll allow לוי Levi
to get paid up. So the גמרא Gemara says, what benefit is
that? Okay, why is that no benefit? Because if he doesn't have
any other land,
then he's not going to lose any other money from ראובן, Reuven,
because you know, it'll, so ראובן, Reuven, he's not going to, it's
not going to, meaning here you have to say land doesn't just
mean land, it means any asset. If he has no other assets,
okay, then whether לוי Levi can collect from this or not collect
from this, I mean לוי. Levi. Whether לוי Levi can collect from
this or not collect from this, לוי Levi is not collecting from
ראובן Reuven because ראובן Reuven has no other assets. So what benefit
does לוי Levi have, what benefit does ראובן Reuven have? Now there's
an obvious answer, somebody will get something. Well, okay, first of all,
he might eventually get assets, and לוי Levi can always collect from
the current assets that ראובן Reuven has. Okay, so that's the most
obvious, right? Is that ראובן, Reuven, even if he has no assets
now, you'd rather not have an outstanding debt. Even if לוי Levi
isn't collecting the debt now because you have no assets, if he
would have collected this you'd be done. Now that he's not collecting
the debt because this land is שמעון, Shimon's, your debt remains. And
you don't want to still be in a state of being indebted.
Kind of obvious. It's kind of obvious. And you might get money
later on. So תוספות Tosafot raise that point, it's bizarre that the
גמרא Gemara did not raise that point, that's the most obvious thing.
The other thing is interesting is that the גמרא Gemara says if
he has no other land, where can לוי Levi collect from? You
could say he has no other land but he has available assets.
Anyway, so you know, chattel. But that's the גמרא Gemara's question, so
let's read the גמרא Gemara's answer. Well let's read
it inside. אי דלית ליה ארעא אחריתי, Ei Deleis Lei Ara Acharisi,
so now if ראובן Reuven has no other land, so and again
maybe that we're going to assume that also means no assets, if
תוספות Tosafot give an answer to, no we'll read the תוספות Tosafot
inside. אי דלית ליה ארעא אחריתי מאי נפקא ליה מיניה? Ei Deleis
Lei Ara Acharisi Mai Nafka Lei Minei? What difference does it make?
לוי Levi isn't going to collect anyway, assuming it means he not
only has no other land but he has no other assets, and
assuming we're going to ignore the fact that he might get assets.
So, if he's never going to pay the debt, what difference does
it make that he pays the debt, pays the debt or doesn't
pay the debt? לוי Levi is never going to collect, he's never
going to take any money anyway out of his own pocket. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, no. מאי נפקא מינה? Mai nafka minei?
לעולם דלית ליה ארעא. Le'olam de'leisa lei ar'a. He doesn't have other
land. דאמר לא ניחא לי לא ניחא דליהוי לוה רשע ולא ישלם.
De'amar lo nicha li, lo nicha de'lehevei lovei rasha ve'lo yeshaleim.
I don't want to be the type of person that borrows money
and never pays it back. So even if the reality is I
will never pay up that debt, and I don't want that to
be who I am, somebody who never pays the debt. So I
want my creditors to be paid off. You really understand that, somebody
borrowed money ten thousand, ten thousand dollars like twenty years ago, they
were having a hard time, and
people still feel, no, I don't want to be indebted, I don't
want to have, I want to pay off that debt even after
the person has basically said to forget about it. So here the
גמרא's Gemara point is, of course, even if it's true that לוי
Levi will never be able to collect any money from ראובן, ראובן
Reuven gains because he's not in a position of never having paid
לוי. Levi. Now the other interesting thing about that is that that's
a type of, on the one hand, it's a very understandable benefit,
like, yeah, that's like really important to people that they should not
be welshers, that they should not be, is that a non-PC term?
Anyway, that they should not, they should not pay off their debt.
But it's not a concrete monetary benefit, right? Maybe it is. Maybe
it means they won't be able to borrow money from other people.
But I'm just raising the question of what type of benefit invalidates
you for testimony? Is the fact that I got this, exactly, so
it's not something that has a clear dollar's value? Maybe it does.
Now my credit rating has gone down, right? So if you think
about it that way, maintaining credit rating has a clear dollar value.
But that's another interesting question. Let's look at תוספות Tosfos where I
just want to read תוספות Tosfos inside. מאי נפקא מינה? Mai nafka
minei? תוספות Tosfos says תימא, Teima, דנפקא מינה שיפטרו אם יתעשר. D'nafka
minei she'yiftaru im yisasher. Right? Of course there's a נפקא מינה nafka
minei that if he gets paid off now, then if he gets
more assets, then if ראובן Reuven, gets more assets later, he'll never
have to pay לוי Levi for sure. ושמא בשביל כן אין לפוסלו
לעדות כיון דהשתא לא מרויח מידי. V'shama bishvil kein ein lefoslo le'eidus
kivan de'hashta lo marviach midi. Since there's no immediate benefit. So that's
an interesting question too, how do you measure benefit? Right now, I'm
not benefiting because he's not taking any money away from me, but
this will benefit me in the future. So there's an interesting question
here about how to measure the type of benefit that invalidates you
for
testimony. Wait, wait, David has had his hand up. David. Liens are
only on land, right? Right. But if it's under my, if I
own it, you can collect from anything. It's only when the borrower
sells that the creditors can only follow the land. But they can
take anything, like, we were saying before,
he might have cash as well.
That's what I said. Another נפקא מינה nafka minei is that ראובן
Reuven doesn't have other land but he has cash. I don't know
why the גמרא Gemara didn't say that either. No, but I mean,
but you're saying if he sold, oh, he has cash. ראובן, Reuven
if ראובן Reuven has cash, that's still constant. לוי, Levi, exactly. לוי
Levi can still come from, oh, but I guess the reason the
גמרא Gemara isn't saying that, oh, no, now it occurs to me,
the reason the גמרא Gemara isn't saying that is if he had
cash, לוי Levi wouldn't be going to שמעון Shimon anyway, because you
first have to try to collect from the borrower. You normally go
to שמעון Shimon if ראובן Reuven, had no money. So actually that's,
that's why the גמרא Gemara doesn't give that as a נפקא מינה
nafka minei because if he had cash, it would never have been
collected from שמעון Shimon to begin with. טוב, Tov, you have a
question? Okay. All right. So here we have this case. You can't
testify for שמעון Shimon because you're going to benefit. What's the benefit?
One benefit we said is that you might have money later, but
תוספות Tosfos says, well, but that's, A, that's in the future and
I think Dov was pointing out under his breath, it's in the
future and it's not even certain. So that's not enough of a
benefit. But the immediate benefit is you don't have an outstanding loan
against you. Even if you're not going to now or later spend
any money, you benefit from the fact that it's not an outstanding
loan against you. Do we correctly assume that all sales of land
are encumbered unless you specifically specify that they're not?
Well, they're encumbered in the sense that anybody who buys land has
to, assumes that if the person he's buying it from took out
a loan, that there are liens on this land. So if that's
what you mean, the answer is yes. Well, you can't specify with
the buyer. It's too late. You have to specify with the person
you were borrowing money from. If I borrow money from you and
then I sell my land to David, I can't say, David, I'm
selling you this piece of land but I'm removing Dov's liens from
it. If I wanted to, if I wanted to keep you off
that land, I would have to specify that in my as part
of the loan. Isn't that a guarantee?
Yes. What saying, I'm removing somebody's lien? No. Right. Thank you. The
way I could protect David, as I don't have the power to
remove your lien, but the way I could protect David is I
can insure it. And I can say, and I can say if
that land gets taken because of Dov's lien, I'm going to reimburse
you. Yeah, exactly. Okay. Thank you, David. Okay. So, the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay.
מכריז רבא, Makhriz Rava, so רבא Rava announced, ואי תימא רב פפא,
V'isima Rav Papa, and some say רב פפא Rav Papa announced,
דסלקי לעילא ודנחתי לתתא, De'salki l'eila v'de'nachi l'tata, those that go up
and come down. Sounds like Jacob's ladder. Those that go to ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and then go back to בבל. Bavel. Did I
skip a line? Oh, סוף סוף רב אידי נמי לא בראשיה ולא
ישאל המלך, sof sof Rav Idi nami lo berasheya velo yishal hamelekh,
oh thank you very much!
That's what's called a שמעתא עדי הדמיות. shemata adei ha-dimyot. Okay, at
the end of the day, just to wrap up. Okay, so at
the end of the day, okay, so I benefit, what do I
benefit? That Levy is going to get paid up. But the גמרא
Gemara says, but I don't benefit, because in that case, Shimon, I
still feel bad for Shimon, I took Shimon's money and he doesn't
wind up with the land, so I'm going to feel... I'm just
exchanging one, you know, if this land was in Shimon's ever,
then Levy would have something against me. Now that Levy is taking
it, right, and you're saying that's going to benefit Levy, I won't
have something against me, but Shimon will have something against me. Because
now Shimon's land will have been taken due to my debts and
now I won't have money to pay up Shimon. So the גמרא
Gemara gives the obvious answer to
that that says, no, הוא דאמר ליה, hu de-amar lei, no, דאמר
ליה אזביני לך שלא באחריות. de-amar lei azveini lakh she-lo be-achrayut. No,
because I said to Shimon, Shimon, why do you think I didn't
insure the plot of land? Okay, so you should have known, you
were taking on risk. Meaning here, Shimon might be upset that the
land was taken, but I could say, you know, you knew the
risk going in. Okay? So the fact that I generally borrowed a
thousand dollars from Levy and am not reimbursing him, that's a real
problem. I'm not paying off my debt. Here, there was no debt
when Levy takes the land. Shimon is angry, but I could say
to Shimon, Shimon, you knew the risks going in. I was not
insuring it. You knew there might be creditors. Don't come complaining to
me. And even if he complains, I'm not the type of person
that borrows money and doesn't pay it back. That's a very different
type of thing. My relationship to Levy, my relationship to Levy, are
you the type of person that sells things that aren't yours? No,
it was mine. It's just happening to be taken by debt. Yeah,
but are you the type of person that sells things when you
know that like, you know, this might be... yeah, I'm the type
of person that knows how to play with the risks in business.
You needed to pay... everything is on the table, you know, you
know that there's always risks with liens on land. I'm selling to
you without insurance. I'm a smart businessman. Shimon got the... wait, wouldn't
you say the same thing in the other case? No, no, that
we don't say. That's immoral, to borrow money and not pay it
up. I don't know, I mean... all right, I'm not debating, I'm
not debating this. We're moving on. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. מכריז רבא ואי תימא רב פפא. Makhriz Rava ve-iteima Rav
Papa. So Rava announced something, Rav Papa announced: דסלקין לעילא ודנחתין לתתא.
de-salkin le-eila u-de-nakhtin le-tata. Those that go up and come
down, to all those that come from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to
בבל Bavel and vice versa, just figuring what that context is. Anyway,
but maybe because it'll we'll see, maybe there's a type of a
saying that had relevance, in more relevance in one geographic community than
in another, maybe to say that it's that it's relevant regardless of
the regardless of the different governments. We'll see, because this has to
do with non-Jews. So maybe he wants to make it clear that
regardless of whether you're living under the, you know, the Persians or
whether you're living under the the Romans, this is going to be
a relevant הלכה. halacha. Okay? האי בר ישראל דזבין ליה חמרא לישראל.
hai bar Yisrael de-zavin lei chamara le-Yisrael. A Jew that sells חמרא,
chamara, here means actually a donkey.
Sometimes it means wine, but from context we're going to see it
clearly means a donkey. Okay. Reuven sells donkey to
Shimon, חבריה. chavreia. וקאתי עכו"ם, ve-ati akum, I'm sure the original גירסא
girsa was גוי Goy or נכרי, Nochri, וקאתי נכרי עליה ואניס ליה.
ve-ati Nochri aleia va-anis lei. And the גוי Goy comes now, the
non-Jew comes and seizes this donkey from Shimon. And says, this donkey
was always mine. So it's similar to like the יהודי Yehudi coming
and saying, this land was always mine, but now it's a non-Jew.
And the question here is, how much do we have to assume
that because they're the people in power, that they're going to be
able to make, you know, to take something without it being justified?
Now there are two scenarios. One scenario is they take it because
they have a winning claim in their secular court of law, which
for us would not be a winning claim because we're playing by
different rules, right? So we would sort of say, no, חזקה כל
מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו. chazaka kol mah she-tachat yad
adam harei hu shelo. And they might say, no, if you can
prove that you owned it a week ago, then we'll assume it's
still yours today, right? It just might be different rules. From our
perspective, you're stealing it; from mine and I the proof is that
I'm holding onto it. From your laws, you know, you're bringing evidence
that it is yours. So that's one scenario. Another scenario is, they
just take it not within the context of their laws, you know,
they just take it because they're in power and they can just
take things that they want to. Okay, so one of one or
two of those are the possible scenarios. Now what's Reuven's responsibility to
Shimon after Shimon's donkey was
taken? Okay. So דינא הוא דמפצי ליה מיניה. Dina hu de-mafzei lei
minei. That Reuven now has a responsibility to try to, רשב"ם Rashbam
says the word מפצי mafzei here means like redeem it. He has
responsibility to try to retrieve the donkey for Shimon. Now that's very
interesting. First of all, how much is that responsibility? So, you know,
so the רשב"ם Rashbam says well, now he needs to try to
bring the evidence in the non-Jewish court of law or whatever it
is to try to help out and defend Shimon. Okay, so that
makes it a different like type of a parallel. Here I sold
it to Shimon and can I be a witness or not, am
I going to benefit or not benefit, etc. Here it's sort of
like not only can I be a witness, I must come to
Shimon's defense. Not because Shimon will have any we'll see whether he
will or won't have any complaint against me and so on, right?
It's
no longer a question, first of all, about me being a kosher
witness and do
I have
a... testify. But more important than allowing me to testify, here I
have a moral, it even uses the word דינא, dina, which sounds
like more like moral, legal obligation to come and try to protect
שמעון. Shimon. That’s the way the רשב״ם Rashbam explains it. רמב״ם Rambam
actually says I have to reimburse שמעון. Shimon. Now that’s a little
crazy. Why is it so much my responsibility? Why do I have
to redeem it from the גזלן? gazlan? Redeem it. The question is,
how do you redeem it? Redeem it through trying to bring witnesses
and evidence and trying to help out שמעון Shimon in court, or
redeem it by buying it back? Right, not paying the גזלן, gazlan,
I have to try to buy it back for שמעון. Shimon. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to clarify where my responsibility
comes to buy it back
for שמעון. Shimon. You could potentially also take them to court or
something like that and get it back when the גזלן gazlan will
listen to you in their courts? Yeah, depending on which version you
have. Right, if it’s a case of courts, maybe it’s still within
their courts, I can win it back. If it’s maybe the גזלן
gazlan who was acting just totally through his force, then maybe I
can buy it back or whatever. Okay. But one way or another,
I have to come and try to help out שמעון. Shimon. And
so the גמרא Gemara says, now what’s the situation? ולא אמרן אלא
שאינו מכיר בשיבת חמורא, ve-lo amrin ella she-eino makir be-shivat chamora, that’s
what phrase we had yesterday. Now
that would that’s only
true if that if שמעון Shimon says, I don’t know,
if שמעון Shimon says to ראובן, Reuven I don’t know, maybe it
really did belong to the non-Jew. The non-Jew is claiming it’s his.
Again, whether he’s claiming it because of דינא דמלכותא, dina de-malchuta, whether
he’s claiming it because who’s going to disagree with the
powerful authorities. Okay, but he’s claiming it’s his. Maybe it really is
his, and therefore, maybe you sold me something you didn’t own. So
therefore, since there is that possibility out there that maybe you actually
sold him something that wasn’t genuinely his, ראובן Reuven has to come
and try to help him out. Okay. Why does ראובן... Reuven, ראובן
Reuven is the seller. אינו מכיר בה eino makir bah because it’s
a donkey. He doesn’t recognize... he does not know that the donkey
genuinely is שמעון’s, Shimon is the daughter of... I mean why is
it the daughter not the son? I guess because it’s all in
the feminine. Okay, anyway, but
he doesn’t know that this donkey was born to שמעון’s Shimon to
ראובן... Reuven... שמעון Shimon got the donkey... I’m going to draw
a
donkey... Yeah... That looks like a side with horns. Anyway, my animals
have... or maybe it’s a little devil with an animal body. Alright.
Okay. So anyway, okay, so the non-Jew here...
what do we call the non-Jew? I think we used to call
him עכו״ם. akum. No, I know but that’s... I just decided that
was being offensive. Let's name a person
then. כל מרדוק. Kol Marduk. Okay, מרדוק. Marduk. Right, so מרדכי. Mordechai.
Okay,
there you go.
Anyway, he comes and he says that’s mine. So now if שמעון
Shimon knows that he's lying and he says, I know this donkey
was born to your donkey, I know I saw it in the
stable or whatever, then שמעון Shimon knows that the non-Jew is just
using force or using דינא דמלכותא, dina de-malchuta, but he knows that
legally it’s mine. So I have no responsibility to him because he
knows that it’s all because he got caught up in the... in
that system of law and that set of powers and that has
nothing to do with me. But
מרדוק Marduk can say it was always his. And שמעון Shimon says,
I don’t know, for all I know מרדוק Marduk is telling the
truth, and maybe you sold me something you don’t own, then I
have to come to שמעון’s Shimon defense. Now the question is that
I have to try to help him out, we understand, right, that
I should be obligated to, as הרמב״ם ha-Rambam says, buy it back
from... like maybe מרדוק Marduk is telling the truth but maybe he
isn't. Like why should all of a sudden that create that level
of... what’s the level of obligation is an important question. Yes, Jenna.
How far back would you go, like what if ראובן Reuven says,
oh but I bought it from so-and-so and I mean that was
a legitimate... Alright, that’s an interesting point. So then how much do
the people up the line have to come and defend and so
on. Yeah. And the irony here also is that if there is
some moral or legal obligation to help him out, so... what about
in a case where it was land? Like the תוספות Tosafot is
saying all these cases where if it’s land and יהודה Yehuda comes
and claims it was always mine, ראובן Reuven is not allowed to
testify because he indirectly benefits. So that technical problem of not being
allowed to
testify
overrides any moral obligation ראובן Reuven might have to try to help
out שמעון, Shimon, right, where here when you don’t have that and
you are allowed then the moral obligation kicks in. So it’s interesting
to line this up opposite the other one. Yes. I’m just trying
to understand where he gets from the word ונסתימהו? u-nesatmeihu? It sounds
like he just seized it by force and didn't redeem it. Right,
so let's see where the גמרא Gemara is going.
I’ve given you both possibilities. Let’s see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ולא אמרן אלא שאינו
מכיר בשיבת חמורא. ve-lo amrin ella she-eino makir be-shivat chamora.
So that’s only if שמעון Shimon says, I don’t know that this
really is your donkey ראובן. Reuven. אבל ידע ליה בשיבת חמורא, aval
yada lei be-shivat chamora, if he really knows it’s ראובן’s Reuven donkey
and he uses a phrase like, I saw it being born to
one of your donkeys in your stable, okay, so בשיבת חמורא, be-shivat
chamora,
לא, lo, then ראובן Reuven has no responsibility to help him out.
ולא אמרן אלא דלא אניס ליה בידיה דאוקמינא. ve-lo amrin ella de-la
anis lei be-yadei de-ukimna. show that you're actually making a genuine claim
of what you believe to be a genuine claim. You're not just
taking because you have power. If you're taking because of your power,
you're going to take it with the saddle, you can take the
whole thing.
But clearly, it's שמעון's Shimon saddle. There's no debate. The question is
whose donkey it is. Nobody questions that it was שמעון's Shimon saddle.
So if he's going to take the donkey with the saddle, then
he's just using force and then ראובן Ruvain has no responsibility. But
if he takes the donkey and leaves the saddle behind, right, then,
oh well, maybe it really is Marduk's, you know? And then ראובן
Ruvain has responsibility. Why should the—I don't really—something very fundamental I don't
get. Like if the עכו"ם Akum takes the חמור Chamor without the
saddle, right? So it's quite believable that he really thinks it's his,
right? Why should there be an obligation to help the other Jew?
I don't
understand. No there is, if he takes it without the saddle.
He took it without the saddle. So he's not just using force.
He genuinely believes and let's even assume, and תוספות Tosfos by the
way assumes that that also might mean let's say he wins it
in דינא דמלכותא, Dina D'Malchusa, right? So he genuinely believes. So you're
saying so why does that create my responsibility to him? Because, because,
because since there's circumstantial evidence that now he's raised the real genuine
possibility that it might have belonged to Marduk and it might have
been illegitimately mine, right? So then given that there's—you mean if I,
ראובן, Ruvain, know that it was mine and I know that Marduk
is lying, why do I have a responsibility? From שמעון's, Shimon let's
look at this way. From שמעון's Shimon perspective, you understand why ראובן
Ruvain has responsibility. You sold me something and now it looks like
you never owned it. Okay, from ראובן's Ruvain perspective, if ראובן Ruvain
knows that he always did legitimately own it, he should have no
moral responsibility because I know Marduk is lying. Okay, so but given
that situation, we're going to require ראובן Ruvain to do what he
can because ראובן Ruvain could always have stolen it and claimed that
he knows that it's not stolen. So since from שמעון's Shimon perspective
that genuine possibility exists, right, we're going to require ראובן, Ruvain, but
I hear your point. Maybe that's why it's דין Din rather than
moral. If it was moral, then I shouldn't have to do anything
if I know that Marduk is lying. But since it's a דין
Din because there is given that there is this possibility, we're going
to demand that ראובן Ruvain do what he can then because that's
dealing with the cases when we're not going to know what the
story is. And if it wasn't Marduk, but like
מרדכי, Mordechai, then that gets back to the question of if it
was a כשר עד, Kasher Ed, and then we're not going to
assume—then it's all going to go by הלכה. Halacha. Here the whole
point is that he took it in a way in הלכה—so Halacha
that's what creates since by הלכה Halacha we know שמעון Shimon owns
it. So that's why now that creates a sort of sense of
how do we respond to it when another system came in. Do
people buy and sell movable property with guarantee?
Unlikely, but I mean it's possible. Let's not worry, we're not dealing
with that case. Okay, so
לא אזל לא אניס ליה לידי ואולוקפא. Lo azel lo anis leh
lidei v'ulookpa. אבל אניס ליה לידי ואולוקפא Aval anis leh lidei v'ulookpa
if Marduk took both the donkey and the saddle, לא, Lo, then
clearly it's just by using force and there would not be an
obligation. אמימר אמר, Ameimar amar, Ameimar says אפילו ליכא כל הני, Afilu
leka kol hani, לא. Lo. Even if there are none of these
things, meaning even if there's all these things that indicate none of
the problems, all these things that indicate that it might genuinely be
Marduk's—שמעון Shimon doesn't know that it was born to ראובן, Ruvain, he
took the donkey and he didn't take the saddle—all those things that
we're saying, oh, so it takes that maybe now it really is
Marduk's, that creates an obligation on ראובן Ruvain to try to help
שמעון Shimon out. He says no, I'm never going to believe any
claim of the non-Jews that could be legitimate.
מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama? בי ידעי דסתמא דעכו"ם אניסי הוא. Bei yadei
d'stama d'Akum anusihu. Because they know, because it's known that
a normal עכו"ם—here Akum I won't say idolater, even though the גמרא
Gemara I'm sure was עכו"ם, Akum, you know, normal gentiles are, you
know, use force to seize things that are not theirs. Extortion. What?
Extortion. שנאמר אשר פיהם דבר שוא וימינם ימין שקר. She'ne'emar asher pihem
diber shav viminam yemin sheker. Okay, so this is obviously one of
those
really difficult גמרות Gemaros because you know you understand historically
why there was a very negative stereotype of non-Jews. I mean, you
know, I mean when they were particularly under the Roman government, and
by the way this might be why we emphasize it was said
both to the Jews who are going to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and the Jews who are coming to בבל, Bavel, because maybe the
point is even though the Roman government was a much more hostile
one and in terms of the Jews and certainly for the period,
the whole Hadrianic persecutions and so on, and חז"ל Chazal viewed the
tax collecting of the Romans as illegitimate, in בבל Bavel it was
a much more friendly government, they viewed the tax collecting—the whole principle
of דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina D'Malchusa Dina is said only in the
בבלי, Bavli, it's not said in ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. It's very clear that
they viewed the government as much more illegitimate, the government of the
Romans than the government of the Persians. Okay, so given that, but
nonetheless, since
still obviously given the historical reality of the Jews' experience in lands
of the non-Jews and so on, you can understand why it creates
this perspective, that they're all violent and thieves and all of that
type of stuff,
you
know. non-Jewish doctors, can we trust this, can we trust that, to
appreciate sometime of the historical setting in which some of these statements
were said, and some פוסקים poskim actually do that and say now
we're dealing with a different reality and we have to assess things
and we have to assess things differently. The issue with doctors for
example comes up about a doctor saying somebody has to eat on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Because there the question isn't, can we trust
non-Jewish doctors, period, but can we trust them if they don't understand
the importance of this question of am I allowed to fast or
not? So that's like a different type of a framing. But nevertheless,
okay, so in general, we see statements like this, and we can
somehow put them in a type of historical context, and פוסקים poskim
have done that and have said that nowadays things could be different.
At least some פוסקים poskim have done that. I think what's troubling
here is that you just got through a גמרא Gemara that actually
was acknowledging that they're not all the same, and was actually acknowledging
that there are some cases that are legitimate and some are not,
particularly one that's sourced in בבל, Bavel, where the government was more
friendly. So after all of that, that סתם אמימר stam Ameimar and
use the voice of the סוגיא sugya saying I don't care about
what the, I don't care about any of this evidence, I don't
want to make distinctions, I just view them all in the exact
same way, it's a little harsh. That's a formalist position, in a
way. You could say it's a formalist position, you could say definitional
and I don't care about the reality. Yeah, or you could say
it's like I just don't trust them. I don't even trust even
when it looks like they're being honest, I just have this blanket
suspicion of non-Jews. I just want to make sure I'm understanding this.
So when
it says אפילו ליכא הני, afilu leika hani, meaning even if he
did leave the saddle and even if he did leave the because
ליכא leika is no, right? So I'm just trying to it doesn't
have the factors that would indicate that he is meaning it doesn't
have the factors that would indicate that he's taking it by force.
Meaning it doesn't have that he took the saddle. It doesn't have
the factor that ראובן Reuven knows that שמעון Shimon knows that it
belonged to whatever. There's none of those factors that indicate he's taken
it by force. Nevertheless I'm going to assume he's taken it by
force. Okay, yeah, Charles. דמי ספק גוי? Dmai sefek goy? Okay,
what does it say about the סתם גוי אנס? stam goy anas?
What's it say after goy? גוי אנס. goy anas. Yeah, okay. All
right, let's take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. One final point about
this, let's take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. דינה דמפצילי. Dina demafztilei.
It says תמיה להרשב״א. temiah le-ha-Rashba. דלמא ליה אייתי סהדי דמרדוך טרפה
ומשלמנא לך. Dilma leh aiti sahadei de-Marduk tarfa u-meshalmana lach. Why doesn't
ראובן Reuven just say to שמעון, Shimon, prove to me that he
was דבי דינא, de-vei dina,
prove to me that מרדוך Marduk took it from you legitimately and
then I'm assuming that מרדוך Marduk actually took it from you forcibly.
If you can prove to me that he legitimately took it, then
I'll reimburse you. Okay? ואפילו גבי ישראל מצי למימר הכי, V'afilu gabi
Yisrael matzi le-meimar hachi, כל שכן לגבי עובד כוכבים. kol sheken legabi
oved kochavim. So he says ויש לומר דמיירי כגון שדייני עובד כוכבים
דייני עמו. V'yesh lomar de-mairi kegon she-dayanei oved kochavim dayanei imo. ודיניהם
הוה דאניא. u-dineihem hovei d'ania. ומשום הכי, u-mishum hachi, so it's another
reason is because it's not a case where it was בית דין,
beit din, it was just דייני עובד כוכבים. dayanei oved kochavim. So
nobody can sort of fault מרדוך Marduk because when two legal systems
come into intersection, מרדוך Marduk has proven to the satisfaction of the
secular court that it's his. So שמעון Shimon is saying reimburse me
because I'm considering you to be a thief. So reimburse I mean
I'm considering it to be stolen goods. And the הלכה halakha actually
is that you actually might have to do that, which is very
interesting in terms of the question of דינא דמלכותא. dina de-malkhuta. When
דינא דמלכותא dina de-malkhuta intersects with, right, דיני ישראל. dinei Yisrael. Because
if you think about it, at the end of the day, putting
aside אמימר, Ameimar, the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is that if
we know or there's an indication that מרדוך Marduk is stealing it,
then ראובן's Reuven off the hook. If מרדוך Marduk wins in secular
court and we're going to use that's what תוספות Tosafot says, the
רמב״ן Ramban says same thing, if מרדוך Marduk wins in secular court,
ראובן Reuven has to reimburse him, which means that we're recognizing the
rulings of secular
court like opposed to אמימר Ameimar says this whole thing is illegitimate,
the whole government is illegitimate, they're all שקרים, shekarim, it's all fast,
that's not ראובן's Reuven responsibility. No, we're actually saying if he wins
in דינא דמלכותא, dina de-malkhuta, that has some weight and that maybe
means that ראובן Reuven did or we're concerned that ראובן Reuven did
sell him stolen goods and ראובן Reuven has to reimburse שמעון. Shimon.
And again do you have to work to try to help שמעון,
Shimon, do you actually have to reimburse him, do you actually have
to buy it back? Yes, Charles. So the question here is, don't
steal is one of the Noahide prohibitions. Are non-Jews permitted to define
theft? Yes, that's part of what דינים dinim is about. Okay, so
now we go on to the next part of the משנה. mishnah.
Can you explain again the question of תוספות?
Tosafot? The question of תוספות Tosafot is that if we're going to
assume if we first assume that מרדוך Marduk did not win it,
did not win it in court, מרדוך Marduk just took it. Okay,
he left behind a saddle. But he just took it. Okay? So
there's an indication maybe it's his because he left behind a saddle,
but there's no official stamp of approval on what. So you שמעון,
Shimon, you come to me and you say, מר Mar took it,
he said it was his. I said, I'll say to you, prove
to me that he legitimately proved it was his and then I'll
reimburse you. Until you do that, I'm going to say I sold
you a donkey that was mine and מר Mar was just סתם
stam taking it. So why do you have a legitimate claim to
ask me to help you out if, okay, there's a little indication
he might have been telling the truth, at least in his own
mind, he thinks he's telling the truth. But I'm claiming he's not.
Why should that create an obligation on me? And תוספות Tosafos says
what creates the right and what תוספות Tosafos says creates the obligation
is not just that he claims it was his, but that he
won in non-Jewish court. Right, exactly. The secular court. Right. So that's
a pretty powerful statement about דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchusa having impact, right?
We don't have a choice anyway. Right, but I could still claim
it's all very nice, but you're going to have to say it's
not that it's legitimate, but what are you going to do? The
constable from the court's going to come. What are you going to
do if they're using force and there's no way to get it
back? And like how long would it last, meaning like that doesn't
mean you're not getting it back, it has to be I'm not
getting it back and it's because I'm assuming that it was stolen
and that it's your responsibility now. So it's not just because the
court ruled it's final,
it's because that still wouldn't create an obligation on me ראובן, Reuven,
it's only because we think that there's some legitimacy to that ruling
so you have a legitimate טענה tayna on me. Imagine like שמעון'ס
Shimon's owned it for 20 years and then there's no. No, שמעון'ס
Shimon's owned 20 years, that would be like the בת חמורה bas
chamora case, then there wouldn't be a responsibility. Oh, you mean שמעון
Shimon owned 20 years after ראובן, Reuven, שמעון Shimon owned it. Yeah,
שמעון Shimon owned it for 20 years and then like some sort
of מלאך malach comes through the town. Right, so that would be
a clear case that there wouldn't be a responsibility, right.
What is the הלכה? halacha? I mean because the fact that the
אמימר Amemar was in Al there, is that what you say הלכה-wise?
halacha Yeah, so I mean thank you for saying that. Okay and
then we really do have to move on, but yes, the רמב"ם
Rambam actually rules like אמימר Amemar and I'll read you the ruling
of the רמב"ם. Rambam. No, he doesn't give that reason, okay, but
I'll read you that ruling and that's actually an important point again
besides the attitude towards non-Jews, it's an important point because of the
question about the legitimacy of דינא דמלכותא. dina d'malchusa. Here I was
talking about how the earlier ruling shows the extent of the legitimacy
of it, and it's all very nice, but what's the פסק psak
at the end? The פסק psak at the end might be rejecting
that. So if you look at the
רמב"ם, Rambam, yeah I did sent, it's י"ט מכירה, Yud-Tes Mechira, hold
on.
Here's what the רמב"ם Rambam
said, he says, okay,
so by the way David,
somebody asked this before and I answered incorrectly. The question was is
there general liability on מטלטלין, mitaltelin, like I have to insure it
or if
they're, well actually let me take a step back. There's two cases,
one is that it's seized by a debt and so on, but
in cases like we saw yesterday where I sell you something and
it's taken from you because the proof was that I never owned
it, then that's not really so much an issue of אחריות, achrayus,
that's like more of a מקח טעות mekach ta'os issue, right? I
never owned it, I sold you something I didn't own. So that
would apply to מטלטלין. mitaltelin. So if this was דיני ישראל dinei
Yisrael and you know this was מרדכי Mordechai and he won it
because it proved that I never owned it, not in collection of
a debt, then I would have to pay off שמעון, Shimon, it
doesn't matter that it's מטלטלין mitaltelin because I sold him, so I
think that's important to also realize here, right? If this was genuinely
won by proof that it was never mine, I would have to
reimburse שמעון. Shimon. So now for the גמרא Gemara it's not genuinely
won, it's won because or whatever it's won because of secular rules
that it wasn't mine. How much does that create a responsibility, right?
So the first opinion is okay, we'll treat it the same as
if מר Mar won in court and now ראובן Reuven has a
responsibility, but the final ruling of אמימר Amemar is ראובן Reuven has
no responsibility even then. And that's the way the רמב"ם Rambam rules.
He says, במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, when is it true
that you would have to reimburse, בשהוציא המקח מיד הלוקח בבית דין
של ישראל, beshehotzi hamekach miyad haloach beveis din shel Yisrael, כגון שהיה
המקח מטלטלין והיו גנובים או גזולים או שהייתה קרקע גזולה או שבא
בעל חוב של מוכר וטרפם מיד הלוקח kegon shehaya hamekach mitaltelin vehayu
genuvim o gezulim o shehayesa karka gezula o sheba ba'al hachov shel
mocher utrafam miyad haloach in the case of קרקע, karka, שהכל בבית
דין של ישראל. shehakol beveis din shel Yisrael.
So if this was taken in a Jewish court, so then I
would have to reimburse him because it was basically a מקח טעות.
mekach ta'os. Okay and that's the position that the גמרא Gemara initially
says would apply even in a non-Jewish court if it was legitimate.
But then the רמב"ם Rambam says, אבל אם עובד כוכבים הוא שהוציא
המקח מן הלוקח בין בדין המלך בין בערכאות שלהם, aval im akum
hu shehotzi hamekach min haloach bein bedin hamelech bein bearkaos shelahem, very
clear, operating within their legal system, right? אין המוכר חייב באחריותו. ein
hamocher chayav beachrayuso. אף על פי שהעובד כוכבים טוען שהמוכר גנב חפץ
זה או גזלו ממנו והביא עדי עובד כוכבים על כך, af al
pi sheha'akum to'en shehamocher ganav chefetz ze o gazlo mimenu veheivi edei
akum al kach, אין המוכר חייב כלום, ein hamocher chayav klum, שזה
אונס הוא, sheze onas hu, ואין המוכר חייב באחריות אונס. ve'ein hamocher
chayav beachrayus ones.
Okay, now that's pretty amazing because the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק, paskens, there's
a question how broadly the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens the principles of
דינא דמלכותא, dina d'malchusa, right? But here basically saying he totally explicitly
says it's working operating within secular law non-Jewish court he won it
fair and square. He won it fair and square, he brought witnesses,
he brought evidence, according to all of that I never owned this
and I should have to reimburse him and I don't have to
reimburse him. I think the whole thing is a scam. I see.
I see it as the רמב"ם's. Rambam I find it astounding that
the רמב"ם Rambam would rule against the legitimacy of a Muslim court
and תוספות Tosafot in favor of the Christian court. Remember תוספות Tosafot
is explaining an earlier stage in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. רמב"ם Rambam
is פוסק'נינג paskening by the last line. Okay. So what I hear
the רמב"ם's Rambam emphasizing though is that word
אונס. ones. In other words, I mean it's not a אונס. ones.
He said he won it from him in בין בדיני המלך בין
בערכאות. bein deini hamelech bein b'arkhaot. No but but I see him
emphasizing that like this was not just justice wasn't done even. How
do you know? How can you decide that without looking at the
case? Yeah again I don't and I do want to say that
there's a number of positions that think that the רמב"ם's Rambam פסק,
psak, דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchuta is very very narrow. There's a שיטת
גאונים shitat geonim that דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchuta refers only to laws
that govern the relationship between the government and the private individual, laws
like paying taxes. But the laws that govern the relationship between individuals,
civil law, okay, according to some שיטה shita is not covered by
דינא דמלכותא. dina d'malchuta. And there's and there's an understanding that based
on other פסקים psakim of the רמב"ם Rambam that רמב"ם Rambam might
hold of that narrow definition. So this certainly seems to reinforce a
very narrow definition of דינא דמלכותא. dina d'malchuta. Okay let's now move
on. אומן אין לו חזקה. Uman ein lo chazakah. אמר רבא. Amar
Rava. Okay so if
you if your dry cleaner says that you know is wearing your
suit and he says you sold it to me, that's not a
חזקה, chazakah, okay? Even though we normally assume something under somebody's possession
is his. Okay so אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא שנו אלא שמסרו
לו בעדים, lo shanu ela shemasro lo b'eidim, אבל מסרו לו שלא
בעדים, aval masro lo shelo b'eidim, מתוך שיכול לומר לו, mittoch sheyachol
lomar lo, לא היו דברים מעולם, lo hayu devarim me'olam, כי אמר
נמי לקוחה היא בידי מהימן. ki amar nami lekucha hee beyadi meheiman.
Okay now
we have to I've got a little confused but hopefully I can
make it simple. עדים, Eidim, לא עדים. lo eidim.
ראה, Ra'ah,
לא ראה. lo ra'ah.
Now
there are going to be four scenarios.
And רבא's Rava going to take one column and אביי's Abaye going
to take one row. Okay one row. In terms of which are
the cases that you don't have a חזקה. chazakah. So here are
the scenarios, okay? I have עדים eidim that David is my dry
cleaner. I have עדים eidim that I gave him my suit.
And now there are two scenarios within that.
Nobody sees him wearing my suit. I say, David, where's my suit?
He says, what do you mean? He says, you know you sold
it to me. He says,
David give it back to me. I gave it to you to
dry clean. He says, no I already gave it back to you
or whatever, you sold it to me, I own it, etc. Okay
so in that am I seeing him wearing it or am I
not seeing him wearing it? What difference does it make? If I'm
seeing him wearing it, then the combination of עדים eidim and seeing
him wearing it means that's the case that's obviously לא חזקה, lo
chazakah, right? Because (A) I know you got it in the context
of doing dry cleaning and I know you're holding onto it now.
So obviously we're going to interpret that that you had it for
dry cleaning purposes, not for owning purposes and that there's no חזקה.
chazakah. The עדים eidim saw you give it to him to dry
clean, yeah. Okay, so you brought עדים eidim to the laundry. Yes,
so this is clear לא חזקה, lo chazakah, yeah. Exactly. Other people
standing around. It's like it's like what's it called? Judge Judy, right?
Oh yes I'm bringing in my two witnesses who were there when
I dropped off my
suit. Okay anyway. Anyway,
okay. Quiet
people,
really, come on. Okay now the question is what about these two
squares? Okay well let's take a look. The case that is most
obvious that I have that that I should have a חזקה chazakah
is this case, right?
Because nobody saw me give a suit to David and nobody sees
it in his hands. Okay and I just accost David on the
street and I say, David where's my Armani suit? and he says,
you sold it to me. So okay he could say I don't
know what the heck you're talking about, right? And he'd be believed.
Nobody sees him wearing it. Okay he could say you gave it
to me and I returned it to you. Anything he could say
he would be believed because there's no עדים eidim I ever gave
it to him and nobody is seeing him wear it right now.
So this is a case that clearly he's believed to say that
it's his. Okay everybody get that? There's no even evidence that it
was ever under his control and I'm not even seeing it with
him now. The question is what do you do about these two
cases? So what רבא's Rava going to say is... רבה, Rabba, excuse
me. Is that the case of לא חזקה lo chazakah is this
case. All the cases where there are עדים eidim that I gave
it to David, since there are עדים eidim I gave it to
him, even if nobody is seeing him wearing it right now... And
he might be able to sort of claim I returned it to
you, right? What's the benefit of not seeing him wearing it right
now? Because he could claim I returned it to you, maybe he'd
be believed or whatever. רבה's Rabba saying no. He still once we
know that he got it as dry clean, even if we're not
seeing it right now, he doesn't have a חזקה, chazakah, okay? Whereas
אביי Abaye is gonna go the other way. I need a different
color. Do I have a different color? Yeah, okay, here we go.
אביי Abaye is gonna go the other way. So אביי Abaye and
we're gonna there's gonna say, okay, that as long as I'm seeing
David with my Armani suit even though nobody knows that I ever
gave it to him, he's a dry cleaner, he's got my suit,
if we know he's got it, then he's not believed to say
that he got it by a purchase. And if he ever wants
to buy my suit he better get a שטר shtar or some
type of witnesses or some type of thing.
People know, people know it's my suit and now they see him
wearing it. Okay, so which of these cases are gonna be the
ones that have no חזקה? chazakah? This obviously has no חזקה, chazakah,
this obviously does. How about these two? Okay, so let's take a
look.
What? אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, לא שנו אלא שמסרו לו בעדים. lo
shanu ela shemasro lo be'eidim. When does he have no חזקה? chazakah?
When there were עדים, eidim, okay? אבל מסרו לו שלא בעדים, aval
masro lo shelo be'eidim,
but if nobody ever saw me gave it to David, מתוך שיכול
לומר לא היו דברים מעולם, mitoch sheyachol lomar lo hayu devarim me'olam,
he could always say, like, even if he's wearing my suit, he
could always say you never gave me this suit to be clean,
you sold it to me. And we never know that this, even
though okay he's a dry cleaner, he's allowed to wear suits. So,
so if nobody ever saw me give him this suit to be
clean, so and he'd be believed to say that, then he's believed
to say it's his. כי אמר ליה נמי לקוחי ki amar lei
nami lekuchi בידי נאמן. beyadi ne'eman. So as long as there are
you'd be believed here because nobody ever saw
because because since nobody saw you have this suit for the purpose
of dry cleaning, you're believed to say that you got this suit
under different conditions. Once we know you got the suit for dry
cleaning, you're not believed even if we're not seeing it in your
possession right now. Okay, so that's so that's רבה. Rabba. רבה. Rabba.
Okay, רבה Rabba says it all goes by עדים. eidim. Okay, in
this case there is no חזקה chazakah and in this case there
is a חזקה, chazakah, okay, because in this case as long as
we don't know that you that you ever got that suit even
if you're a dry cleaner, then you're not then you're believed to
say that you got it legitimately. Okay, that is רבה's Rabba position.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said, אי הכי אפילו
בעדים נמי, i hachi afilu be'eidim nami, מתוך שיכול לומר החזרתי לך,
mitoch sheyachol lomar hehzarti lach, כי אמר נמי לקוחי ki amar nami
lekuchi בידי נאמן. beyadi ne'eman. Now אביי Abaye says so with עדים
eidim if you go down to this square, so why you should
also be believed according to you? Because אביי Abaye assumes if I
gave if I gave David my suit with עדים eidim and then
I said David, give me back my suit, okay? And he says
I gave it back to you. Is he believed? Is he believed
to say this is why we use tickets, right, to prove who's
got the suit and whose suit can we assume has it or
whatever. So but if we don't have tickets that we're gonna use,
so if I say David, where's my suit and he says I
gave it back to you, אביי's Abaye assuming he'd be believed to
say that since we're not seeing him holding onto it. So since
even if there were עדים eidim if we're not seeing him holding
onto it if he'd be believed to say he gave it back,
he should be believed to say he bought it because he could
just as easily say he gave it back.
Why is he believed that he gave it back given the fact
that wouldn't it be המלווה את חבירו בעדים צריך לפורעו בעדים? hamalveh
et chaveiro be'eidim tzarich lifro be'eidim? Yeah but there's a general question
there's a question like המלווה את חבירו בעדים צריך לפורעו בעדים hamalveh
et chaveiro be'eidim tzarich lifro be'eidim אין צריך לפורעו בעדים. ein tzarich
lifro be'eidim. So yeah meaning all the עדים eidim prove is that
he originally got it but they don't prove that he's still holding
onto it. So that becomes this question about what type of standard
of proof is required to prove you know that the other thing
was not satisfied. But yeah רבה's Rabba presumption is makes I think
the most intuitive sense. If I gave it to you with עדים
eidim you're gonna have to demonstrate to prove that you gave it
back. But okay so anyway let's take... אמר ליה רבה, Amar lei
Rabba, so רבה Rabba said, מי סברת? mi savart? I don't agree
with
you אביי. Abaye. מי סברת המקדיש את חבירו בעדים אינו צריך להחזירו
לו בעדים? mi savart hamakdeish et chaveiro be'eidim eino tzarich lehachazir lo
be'eidim? Who who says that David doesn't have to return it to
me with עדים? eidim?
If if if I said to David where's my suit and he
says I gave it back, I can't believe him. לא סלקא דעתך,
lo salka da'atach, אלא המפקיד
אצל חבירו בעדים צריך להחזירו לו בעדים. ela hamapkid et chaveiro be'eidim
tzarich lehachazir lo be'eidim. No, I hold that David even if I
say where's my suit and he says I gave it back to
you, he's not believed and I can sue him. If I got
עדים eidim at the time he needs to have עדים eidim in
the return. Okay, so David asked a good question like, you know,
what's our point of departure here? But this is why there's a
debate because the גמרא Gemara understands just because normally עדים eidim prove
that I still owe something, here they just prove that I at
one time owed it but we assume eventually the loan is going
to be paid and the פקדון pikadon is going to be given
back. So how do does that create a shift of presumption of
proof onto you know onto me not shift the presumption of proof.
But anyway what רבה Rabba is saying is since I told him
these cases David is not believed to say he has it, he
he gave it back to me, then he also doesn't have a
חזקה. chazakah. In these cases where we never know that David had
it to begin with, he does have a חזקה. chazakah. That's רבה.
Rabba. Okay. Now
מיתיבי אביי, Meisive Abaye, אביי Abaye asks on this. רב אבודימי דאומן
Rav Abudimi d'Uman וטליתא ביד כובס. v'Talisa b'yad Koves. What's that? כובס.
Koves. אומר
לו מה טיבו אצלך. Omer lo mah tivo etzlecha. You see your
slave by your by a blacksmith. He's apprenticing himself by the blacksmith.
Or you see your garment at the dry cleaner. The dry cleaner.
And he says what's it doing? את מכרת לי את נתת לי
במתנה. At makarta li at natata li b'matanah. What do you mean?
You sold me this slave. You sold me this garment. Okay. לא
אמר כלום. Lo amar klum. He's not believed. That's a case of
an אומן uman is not קנה koneh right with a חזקה. chazakah.
Okay, now, if he says בפני אמרת לו למוכרו וליתנו לו במתנה
דבריו קיימין. Befanai amarta lo l'mochro v'lisno lo b'matanah devarav kayamin. If
you told me in his presence to sell it to him, he
is believed. What does that mean?
Told me in whose presence? And why all of a sudden is
he believed if this is an אומן uman who isn't believed when
he said he bought it from me directly? Why is he believed
to say when he bought it from me in somebody's presence? What's
going on here? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא רישא ומאי
שנא סיפא? Mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa? And the גמרא Gemara
says wait, what's he talking about here in the end? אמר רבא
סיפא באחר מיתחת יד אחר. Amar Rava seifa b'acher mitachas yad acher.
No, no, no. Here's what the end means. It means if I
say to the dry cleaner what are you doing with my suit?
He says you sold it to me, he's not believed. But if
I see Jenna with my suit and I say Jenna what are
you doing with my suit? והאמר לה אחר V'ha'amar lah acher and
Jenna says בפני אמרת לו למוכרו וליתנו לו במתנה Befanai amarta lo
l'mochro v'lisno lo b'matanah and Jenna says because you told when I
was at the dry cleaner picking up the dry cleaning, David told
me that you had asked him to, no, not David told me,
I saw you, don't you remember though, we bumped into each other
at the dry cleaner and you said right there to David, you
said you know what, give my suit to give my suit to
Jenna. So you're saying that I gave that suit to you. David
gave it to you, but you heard me tell David to give
it to you. So in that case, even though she's getting it
from the dry cleaner, she is believed because if she wanted to
lie, she would just say she got it straight from me. Okay.
So if David says, right? If okay. וכי אמר ליה נמי בפני
אמרת לו למוכרו דבריו קיימין ומהימן. V'chi amar leh nami befanai amarta
lo l'mochro devarav kayamin u'meheman. Okay. So
that's the case for if I say to David what are you
doing with that suit and he says you sold it to me
he's not believed. If I say to Jenna what are you doing
with that suit and she says you told David to give it
to me and I heard you tell David she is believed. Wonderful.
Let's get back to the first case. יש מיגו. Yesh migo. Right.
זה מיגו. Ze migo. Exactly. Let's get back to the first case
where where David is not believed when he says that that I
sold him the suit. So קתני מיהת רישא Katani miahs reisha ראה
ra'ah that I saw David holding on to the suit, right, that's
what it says. You saw your suit in somebody else's hands. That
shows that the key issue here is ראה, ra'ah, the key factor
is not not whether there were עדים, edim, but whether it was
ראה ra'ah or not. If he saw it David holding on to
a suit, my suit, there's no
חזקה. chazakah.
Okay, so קתני מיהת רישא ראה היכי דמי אי דאיכא עדים למה
לי ראה נחזי סהדי ונשתוק. Katani miahs reisha ra'ah heichi dami i
d'ika edim lamah li ra'ah nechezei sahadi v'nishtok. According to you, רבא,
Rava, who needs ראה? ra'ah? If you're
רבא, Rava, excuse me, if there were עדים, edim, you say עדים
edim always needs no חזקה. chazakah. So don't tell me ראה, ra'ah,
tell me whether there were witnesses and how he got it in
the first place. אלא לאו דליכא עדים, Ela lav d'leika edim, it
must be that there are no witnesses and the key question is
did you see him holding on to it or not? וכי ראה
מאי הוי ליה? V'chi ra'ah mai havi leh? So you see that
the key factor is not whether it was given with witnesses, the
key factor is whether it was given whether you saw it in
the hand. So the גמרא, Gemara, you don't understand? No, because
what? Because if he thinks he bought it from you then of
course he has it. What does it matter that... No, because if
it was לא ראה lo ra'ah he could say, he could claim
if he wanted to lie that he doesn't, he never has it.
Or that he never had it. Right. So you see the point
about these two things is if he didn't see it he could
claim he never had it, he never had it. And if there
were, wait which is the other one? And if and if, oh,
and here he
could claim he could claim like even though you see that he
has it now he claims he never got it in the context
of dry cleaning. But he bought it from me. Right, but then
that's based on עדים, edim, not on... Right, but this ברייתא braisa
says that because I saw it in his hand he's not believed.
Right, but that's not, that's just where I'm not understanding why, like
why can't he still say, yeah of course I have it, I
bought it from you? Because Abaye's contention is is that because in
general you give your clothes to a dry cleaner, you're never, you
can never believe if a dry cleaner is wearing somebody's clothes we
knew belonged to somebody else, he's just because of his profession he's
never believed what the context is that he has those clothes. So
he better get a good receipt or a שטר. shtar. Right. So
okay, yes, it's true, it's not like starting with evidence that you
got it in one context, it's a generic, being אביי Abaye makes
sense about the משנה, Mishnah, because the משנה Mishnah says a dry
cleaner doesn't have a חזקה. chazakah. It's not a case-by-case, I saw
you got this suit in this context. It's generally, since you're generally
a dry cleaner, we're going to assume if you have other people's
clothes, it's because you got them for dry cleaning unless you can
prove otherwise. Okay? So yes, the thank you, that's why ראתה ra'ah
matters. Even if we don't know how you got this, because you're
a dry cleaner we're going to assume you got it for the
purpose of dry cleaning. So let's just see how רבא Rava answers,
I'm going to end with that right now. So when it says
אלא בלא איכא עדים וראתה מאי טעמיה פסולה, Ella belo ika eidim
vera'ata mai ta'ameih pesula, so you see the key question is even
without עדים, eidim, if you see the guy holding onto it and
he's a dry cleaner, you cannot assume that it's legitimately his. If
you don't see and he could always deny it, you can't assume
it's his. So it says לא לעולם דאיכא עדים, Lo le'olam de'ika
eidim, there are witnesses. והוא דראתה. Vehu de-ra'ata. So he says no,
no, actually the reason the ברייתא braita says ראתה ra'ata is because
you need both. For David not to have a חזקה, chazakah, this
is really shrinking it, it's only this case which is the most
obvious case. There were witnesses he got it for dry cleaning and
you saw it. That's the obvious case. So that's why you need
ראתה. ra'ata. Only when the two things combined does David not have
the חזקה. chazakah. So אביי Abaye says back one minute, והא את
הוא דאמרת, Veha at hu de-amart, המפקיד אצל חברו בעדים צריך להחזירו
בעדים. Hamifkid etzel chaveiro be-eidim tzarich lehachziro be-eidim.
But you said it's all about עדים, eidim, and if there are
עדים, eidim, even if it was לא ראתה, lo ra'ata, David wouldn't
be believed because he wouldn't be believed to say he gave it
back. It says הדר בי, Hadar bi, all right, I take it
back.
So the evidence of the ברייתא braita is the last sentence. The
evidence of the ברייתא braita is that for an אומן uman not
to have a חזקה, chazakah, it's necessary that we see him wearing
it, otherwise he could always claim he doesn't have it all together.
For אביי, Abaye, that's all that matters. ראתה Ra'ata never has a
חזקה, chazakah, לא ראתה lo ra'ata always has a חזקה. chazakah. רבא,
Rava, who emphasized עדים eidim because of this ברייתא, braita, is forced
to concede that ראתה ra'ata matters and winds up saying that it's
only when you have both things coming
together you're not going to have a חזקה. chazakah. It's so you
see, because you don't have the עדות eidut of the returning, only
of the giving at the beginning. Right. Well he concedes a weakness
in the עדות, eidut, you need something else. Right, yeah, this case
of both, right, right. Anyway, yeah. So, yeah, because he would be
believed to say he gave it back. Exactly. So you need to
have both of them coming together. All right, so that's the... clean
off the table. What?